Ali-Taabesh Sayyed

■ 469-955-1847 | Malitsayyed@gmail.com | DinkedIn | GitHub | US Citizen

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with over a year of experience. A fast learner and problem-solver with strong analytical/interpersonal skills. Strong project and time management skills to exceed expectations. Biochemistry (STEM) major with 4.0 GPA Summa Cum Laude.

SKILLS

Technical Skills

- Programming Languages: Java, Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, Go (Golang), HTML, CSS, SQL
- Frameworks & Tools: Django, Angular, React, Git, GitHub, N8N (Workflow Automation), Dockers, Kubernetes, Terraform, Virtual Machines, Google Cloud Platform, Google App Scripts, vim
- Databases: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, SQLite
- Development: Data Structures & Algorithms (DSA), Object-Oriented Programming (OOP), Functional Programming, REST APIs
- Other: HTTP Networking, IP Subnetting, Debugging, Problem-Solving, Analytical Abilities, Agentic Frameworks, AI-Agents Information Technology
 - Operating Systems: Microsoft Windows, Mac OS X & Linux (Ubuntu & Kali)
 - Microsoft Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel), Google Suite (Docs, Slides, Sheets), Adobe (Premier, Photoshop, After Effects)

Communication & Interpersonal

- Excellent Communication Skills, Persuasive Messaging, Storytelling, Active Listening, Conflict Management Skills
- Team player with a positive attitude, confident self-starter, entrepreneurial and risk-taking ability

EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer- BRAIN AI

Nov 2024 – Present

- Architected and implemented data pipelines using voice AI solutions, reducing manual client processes by ~80%, leveraging our Golang-based microservices.
- Developed automated workflows, frontend interfaces, and built custom testing tools—fully adopted by customer departments.
- Independently mastered complex backend systems, delivered custom automation solutions, and rapidly adopted new technologies.

Software Engineer - Legal Pro System

Aug 2024 – Nov 2024

- Worked on full stack development, enabling lawyers to efficiently manage clients, cases, and communications.
- Developed a real-time chat system using Django and Angular, delivering a WhatsApp Web-like user experience and architected to support 1,000+ concurrent users.

Biomedical Nano-Devices Research Assistant/ Biology TA

June 2018 - May 2021

- Assisted in lab-based R&D on wearable nano-sensors for inflammation biomarkers; supported experimental trials and data analysis that informed ~4 peer-reviewed publications.
- Curated content and led engaging Biology classes, recognized by students and faculty as a top-performing TA.

PROJECTS

Developer Portfolio: https://www.alitsayyed.com

Full Stack Freelancer Review Platform

• Built a full-stack web app using Django, Angular, and PostgreSQL to simulate a Trustpilot-like review system. Implemented RESTful APIs and designed scalable database schemas to support user reviews and ratings.

Go RSS Aggregator Backend

• Developed a Go-based backend server featuring user authentication and optimized RSS feed collection, focusing on efficient concurrency and data handling.

Amazon Clone Frontend

• Developed a responsive e-commerce frontend using HTML, CSS, and vanilla JavaScript. Demonstrated deep understanding of DOM manipulation and frontend rendering principles underlying modern frameworks.

Data Structure and Algorithm Implementations

• Created puzzle solver with A* search algorithm, percolation determination with union find, and nearest neighbor search with Kd-Trees.

EDUCATION

University of Princeton/Helsinki Online Course - Computer Science

Sept 2023-May 2024

• Courses: Data Structures and Algorithms, Java, Python

The University of Texas at Dallas - B.S. Biochemistry (4.0 GPA Summa Cum Laude)

Aug 2018 - May 2022

AWARDS

Dean's List, Richardson, TX

Aug 2018 – May 2022

• Maintained top 10% GPA in the School of Natural Sciences and Mathematics.

AES Distinction Scholarship, Richardson, TX

• Awarded a full-ride scholarship to high school students with competitive grades.